<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>D. Tomov's Ramblings Repository</title><link>https://zakupower.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on D. Tomov's Ramblings Repository</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2022 21:07:13 +0300</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://zakupower.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Considerations for running backend applications in multi-instance environment</title><link>https://zakupower.github.io/posts/multi-instance/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2022 21:07:13 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://zakupower.github.io/posts/multi-instance/</guid><description>Scheduled Jobs Scheduled jobs are to be avoided in multi-instance environment. The application I was working on relied on scheduled jobs for a lot of its operation. I would say scheduled jobs are very common in a lot of modern applications, so you have two choices.
Move all the scheduled jobs to a second application which would act as a worker application. - this is what my team did, because we already had such an application, but we weren&amp;rsquo;t fully utilizing it and still had jobs in our API application Introduce a locking mechanism for your scheduled jobs e.</description><content>&lt;h2 id="scheduled-jobs">Scheduled Jobs&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Scheduled jobs are to be avoided in multi-instance environment. The application I was working on relied on scheduled jobs for a lot of its operation. I would say scheduled jobs are very common in a lot of modern applications, so you have two choices.&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Move all the scheduled jobs to a second application which would act as a &lt;strong>worker application&lt;/strong>. - this is what my team did, because we already had such an application, but we weren&amp;rsquo;t fully utilizing it and still had jobs in our API application&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Introduce a &lt;strong>locking mechanism for your scheduled jobs&lt;/strong> e.g. &lt;a href="https://github.com/lukas-krecan/ShedLock">Shedlock&lt;/a> - this is probably the choice for most application, since starting a new application that would just serve as a worker is unthinkable/unnecessary for most projects&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="logging">Logging&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I would say the first step would be to look at everything you are logging, and try to &lt;strong>reduce your logs as much as possible&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Your logs are very important for your application, so when increasing the instance count you would have a lot more logs than with a single application. If you are not using a &lt;strong>log collecting, storing and searching solution&lt;/strong> you should introduce one now. One good such solution would be the &lt;a href="https://www.elastic.co/what-is/elk-stack">ELK stack&lt;/a> which many modern applications use, which includes Elasticsearch, Logstash and Kibana for very organized way of viewing your logs (if configured correctly).&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>TODO: Continue
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre></content></item><item><title>README.MD</title><link>https://zakupower.github.io/readme/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 23:21:13 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://zakupower.github.io/readme/</guid><description>I am using this &amp;ldquo;Ramblings Repository&amp;rdquo; to document my experiments or research in different topics that are of interest to me. I do not promise that everything written here is the most correct, but it is correct to me at the time of writing it. If you want to discuss any of the topics in this repository you can message me on LinkedIn or Twitter using the links bellow.
Key Value Name Dimitar Tomov Currently Senior Software Engineer @ Scalefocus From Burgas, Bulgaria Programming Languages Java, Kotlin Technical Interests Backend, Spring, Cloud, Architecture Design, Clean Code Interests Video Games, Movies, Cooking, Biking LinkedIn Dimitar Tomov Twitter @dimtomov Currently Reading About Kotlin for Backend development</description><content>&lt;p>I am using this &amp;ldquo;Ramblings Repository&amp;rdquo; to document my experiments or research in different topics that are of interest to me. I do not promise that everything written here is the most correct, but it is correct to me at the time of writing it. If you want to discuss any of the topics in this repository you can message me on LinkedIn or Twitter using the links bellow.&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th style="text-align:right">Key&lt;/th>
&lt;th>Value&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:right">Name&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Dimitar Tomov&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:right">Currently&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Senior Software Engineer @ &lt;a href="https://www.scalefocus.com/">Scalefocus&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:right">From&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Burgas, Bulgaria&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:right">Programming Languages&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>Java, Kotlin&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:right">Technical Interests&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>Backend, Spring, Cloud, Architecture Design, Clean Code&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:right">Interests&lt;/td>
&lt;td>Video Games, Movies, Cooking, Biking&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:right">LinkedIn&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/dimitar-tomov/">Dimitar Tomov&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:right">Twitter&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dimtomov">@dimtomov&lt;/a>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td style="text-align:right">Currently Reading About&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;code>Kotlin for Backend development&lt;/code>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table></content></item><item><title>Initial Commit</title><link>https://zakupower.github.io/posts/initial-commit/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2022 23:10:28 +0300</pubDate><guid>https://zakupower.github.io/posts/initial-commit/</guid><description>Hello World!</description><content>&lt;p>Hello World!&lt;/p></content></item></channel></rss>